John L. McCrea Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
John L. McCrea Papers 1898-1984 (bulk 1914-1966)
MSS81333
McCrea, John L. (John Livingstone), 1891-
5,255 items
14 containers
5.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officer, aide to President Franklin D. Roosevelt, and insurance executive. Correspondence, speeches, writings, subject files, and photographs relating primarily to McCrea's career as a naval officer.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Berkey, Russell S. (Russell Stanley), 1893-1985.; Blandy, William H. P. (William Henry Purnell), 1890-1954.; Campbell, E. H. (Edward Hale), 1872-1946.; Conolly, Richard L. (Richard Lansing), 1892-1962.; Denfeld, Louis E. (Louis Emil), 1891-1972.; Dennison, Robert L. (Robert Lee), 1901-1980.; Fechteler, W. M. (William Morrow), 1896-1967.; Hart, Thomas Charles.; Hassett, William D., 1880-1965.; Hicks, Walter A. (Walter Alexander), 1892-; Ingram, Jonas H. (Jonas Howard), 1886-1952.; McCandlish, B. V. (Benjamin Vaughan), 1886-; McCrea, John L. (John Livingstone), 1891-1990.; Nimitz, Chester W. (Chester William), 1885-1966.; Pugh, Herbert Lamont, 1895-; Quiggle, Lynne C. (Lynne Cline), 1906-1958.; Rodman, Hugh, 1859-1940.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Smith, A. E. (Allan Edward), 1892-1987.; Smith, Arthur St. Clair, 1873-1942.; Stark, Harold R. (Harold Raynsford), 1880-1972.; Tolley, Kemp, 1908-; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.
Organizations
Combined Chiefs of Staff (U.S. and Great Britain); Germany. Kriegsmarine--History--World War, 1914-1918.; Iowa (Ship); United States. Navy--Foreign service--Central America.; United States. Navy--Foreign service--Guam.; United States. Navy--Foreign service--Pacific Area.; United States. Navy. Asiatic Fleet.; United States. Navy. Cruiser Division One.; United States. Navy. Naval District, 1st.; United States. Navy. Pacific Fleet.; United States. Navy. Special Service Squadron.; United States. Office of the Chief of Naval Operations.
Subjects
World War, 1914-1918--Europe.; World War, 1914-1918--Naval operations, American.; World War, 1914-1918--Naval operations, British.; World War, 1939-1945--Alaska.; World War, 1939-1945--Soviet Union.
Places
Aleutian Islands (Alaska)--History.; Camp David (Md.); France--Armed Forces--Mobilization.; Guam--Politics and government.; Guam--Social conditions.; Kuril Islands (Russia)--History.; Nicaragua--Politics and government--1909-1937.; Nicaragua--Social conditions.; Panama--Politics and government--1903-1946.; Panama--Social conditions.
Titles
John L. McCrea papers (Naval Historical Foundation collection)
Occupations
Insurance executives.; Naval officers.
Provenance
The papers of John L. McCrea, naval officer, aide to President Franklin D. Roosevelt, and insurance executive, were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1990 and converted to a gift in 1998.
Transfers
Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the John L. McCrea Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of John L. McCrea are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1891, May 29 Born, Marlette, Mich.
1915 Graduated, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1915 1919 Served aboard New York (battleship)
1919 1921 Served aboard New Mexico (battleship) Aide to Admiral Hugh Rodman, commander in chief, United States Pacific Fleet
1921 1922 Served aboard destroyers Burns, Babbitt, and Zeilin
1922 Executive officer, Ramapo (fuel oil tanker)
1923 1924 Attended Naval War College, Newport, R.I.
1924 1926 Commanded Bittern (mine sweeper)
1926 1929 Assigned to judge advocate general
1929 Received bachelor of law degree, George Washington University, Washington, D.C.
1929 1931 Aide and flag secretary to the commander, special service squadron operating in Central American waters
1932 1934 Aide to Orin G. Murfin, judge advocate general
1934 Received master of law degree, George Washington University, Washington, D.C.
1934 1936 Navigator, Astoria (cruiser)
1936 1937 Executive officer of naval station and aide for civil administration, Guam
1938 1940 Executive officer, Pennsylvania (battleship)
1941 Aide to Harold R. Stark, chief of naval operations Naval secretary at the first meetings of the Combined Chiefs of Staff
1942 1943 Naval aide to President Franklin D. Roosevelt
1943 1944 Commanded Iowa (battleship)
1944 1945 Commanded Cruiser Division One in attacks on Japanese installations in the Aleutian and Kurile islands
1946 Deputy chief of naval operations
1948 1949 Deputy commander, United States Pacific Fleet
1949 1952 Director of staff, Personnel Policy Board, United States Navy
1952 1953 Commander, First Naval District
1953 Retired from Navy Vice-president for client relations, John Hancock Mutual Life Insurance Co.
1966 Retired from John Hancock Mutual Life Insurance Co.
1990, Jan. 25 Died, Needham, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of John L. McCrea (1891-1990), Franklin D. Roosevelt's naval aide during the early part of World War II, span the years 1898-1984, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1914-1966. The collection is organized into general correspondence, speeches and writings, and subject files. The general correspondence is arranged chronologically and spans most of McCrea's naval career (1914-1953), a second career as an insurance executive (1953-1966), and his postretirement through 1984. McCrea served from 1915 to 1919 aboard the battleship New York, flagship of Adm. Hugh Rodman's Division Nine, a force of United States warships cooperating with the British Grand Fleet in European waters during World War I. Correspondence from this period relates to relations between the United States and the British navies and to the surrender of the German High Seas Fleet in 1918. McCrea also served under Rodman as an aide (1919-1921) during the admiral's command of the United States fleet in the Pacific. McCrea and Rodman maintained a correspondence well into the 1930s. From 1929 to 1931, McCrea was aide and flag secretary to E. H. Campbell and Arthur St. Clair Smith, successive commanders of a special service squadron operating in Central American waters. Correspondence from this period is a rich source on military, political, and social conditions in Nicaragua and Panama.
McCrea's service with the Naval Government of Guam (1936-1937), as executive officer of the naval station on the island and as aide for civil administration, generated correspondence with governor B. V. McCandlish and others about social, military, and political conditions on Guam. During the period 1941-1943, McCrea served as aide to chief of naval operations Harold R. Stark, as naval secretary at the first meeting of the Combined Chiefs of Staff, and as naval aide to President Franklin D. Roosevelt. From 13 December 1940 to 31 January 1941, while working for Stark, McCrea traveled to the Philippines to appraise the battle readiness of the United States Asiatic Fleet and the fitness of its commander, Thomas C. Hart. Included in the correspondence for the period 1941-1943 are memoranda from Roosevelt and correspondence with several White House staffers, especially William D. Hassett, personal secretary to Roosevelt, and Harry S. Truman.
Prominent in the general correspondence are many letters from McCrea's duty aboard a variety of naval vessels, including billets as navigator of the cruiser Astoria (1934-1936), executive officer of the fuel oil tanker Ramapo (1922) and the battleship Pennsylvania (1938-1940), and commander of the mine sweeper Bittern (1924-1926) and the battleship Iowa (1943-1944). McCrea maintained correspondence with former shipmates, commissioned and enlisted, over long periods of time. Prominent in this group were Allan E. Smith and Lynne C. Quiggle. Other areas of McCrea's naval career well documented in the general correspondence include his command of Cruiser Division One against Japanese installations in the Aleutian and Kurile islands during 1944-1945 and his postwar service as deputy chief of naval operations, deputy commander of the United States Pacific Fleet, director of staff for the Personnel Policy Board, and commander of the First Naval District. Prominent correspondents not previously cited include Russell S. Berkey, William H. P. Blandy, Richard L. Conolly, Louis E. Denfeld, Robert L. Dennison, W. M. Fechteler, Thomas C. Hart, Walter A. Hicks, Jonas H. Ingram, Chester W. Nimitz, Earle T. Oakes, Herbert Lamont Pugh, and Kemp Tolley.
The subject file contains topical files that dovetail with subjects covered in the general correspondence, such as Nicaragua and Guam. Of interest are files related to McCrea's service as a presidential naval aide, the battleship Iowa, and Anna M. Rosenberg, who was assistant secretary of defense for manpower during the Korean War. Of interest in the speeches and writings file is McCrea's account of his midshipman days, which included a memorable 1914 summer cruise to the Mediterranean aboard the battleship Idaho. This experience afforded McCrea the opportunity to witness the French mobilization for World War I. Also included are a diary covering McCrea's stint as naval aide to Franklin D. Roosevelt, an account of the establishment of the presidential retreat at Camp David, Maryland, and McCrea's history of the Iowa.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- General correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1915-1940, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1941-1942, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1943-1945, (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1946-1947, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1948 (Box 4)
    - Jan.-Mar. (Box 4)
    - Apr.-Dec., (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1949 (Box 5)
    - Jan.-Aug., (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - Sept.-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1950, (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1951 (Box 6)
    - Jan.-Mar. (Box 6)
    - Apr.-Dec., (4 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1952-1953, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1954-1960, (7 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1961-1984, undated, (10 folders) (Box 9)
- Speeches and writings (Box 9)
  - Speeches (Box 9)
    - By McCrea (Box 9)
      - 1943-1949, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - 1950-1966, undated, (9 folders) (Box 10)
    - By others, 1945-1949, (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Writings (Box 11)
    - By McCrea (Box 11)
      - Account of the beginnings of Camp David presidential retreat, undated (Box 11)
      - Accounts of incidents aboard Iowa, undated (Box 11)
      - Diary, presidential naval aide, 1942 (Box 11)
      - History of the USS Iowa, undated (Box 11)
      - Narrative of naval career, 1911-1918, undated (Box 11)
      - Notes on naval operations against the Kurile Islands and Franklin D. Roosevelt's health, undated (Box 11)
    - By others (Box 11)
      - Charlton, Linda, "Camp David: Secluded Retreat of Presidents," 1972 (Box 11)
      - Kahn, David, "Roosevelt, Magic, and Ultra," undated (Box 11)
      - Pugh, H. L., "A One Man Safari," 1948 (Box 11)
      - Whitehill, Walter M., "A Postscript to Fleet Admiral King," undated (Box 11)
- Subject file (Box 11)
  - Appointment books (Box 11)
    - 1949 (Box 11)
    - 1950 (Box 12)
  - Biographical materials (Box 12)
    - Biographies, 1945-1963, undated (Box 12)
    - Clippings, 1944-1966, undated (Box 12)
    - Photographs, 1942-1958, undated (Box 12)
  - Clippings and press releases, 1944-1958, undated (Box 12)
  - Duty assignment orders, 1915-1953, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Guam and the Mariana Islands, 1898-1947, undated (Box 12)
  - Hassett, William D., 1943-1965 (Box 13)
  - Idaho (battleship), page from logbook, 1914 (Box 13)
  - Iowa (battleship) (Box 13)
    - Clippings, 1943-1951, undated (Box 13)
    - Franklin D. Roosevelt's cruise, 1948-1958, undated (Box 13)
    - Investigation of grounding, 1943 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1943-1952, undated (Box 13)
    - Photographs, 1943, undated (Box 13)
    - Speeches, 1943 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1941-1946, undated (Box 13)
  - Nicaragua, 1928 (Box 13)
  - Officer's qualification jacket, 1938-1951 (Box 13)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Box 13)
    - Death of, 1945 (Box 13)
    - Handwritten note and drawing by, undated (Box 13)
    - Photographs, 1942, undated (Box 13)
  - Rosenberg, Anna M., 1951 (Box 13)
  - Social engagements (Box 14)
    - Calendars and memoranda, 1948-1949 (Box 14)
    - Invitations, 1949-1951, undated (Box 14)
  - Surrender of the German High Seas Fleet, 1918 (Box 14)
  - Unification of the armed services, 1949 (Box 14)
  - United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md. (Box 14)
    - Class of 1915, 1955-1957 (Box 14)
    - Holloway plan and related material, 1949 (Box 14)
  - Warm Springs Foundation, 1947, undated (Box 14)